Information technology grows in an exponential manner.
تقنية المعلومات تنمو بطريقة أسية
It's not linear. And our intuition is linear.
إنها ليست خطية. في حين أن حدسنا خطي
When we walked through the savanna a thousand years ago
حين مشينا في السافانا منذ ألف عام
we made linear predictions where that animal would be,
قمنا بتنبؤات خطية عن مواقع الحيوانات
and that worked fine. It's hardwired in our brains.
وعمل ذلك جيدا. إنه مبرمج في عقولنا
But the pace of exponential growth
ولكن وتيرة النمو الأسي
is really what describes information technologies.
هو ما يصف تقنية المعلومات
And it's not just computation.
وذلك ليس في الحساب فقط
There is a big difference between linear and exponential growth.
هناك فرق كبير بين النمو الخطي والأسي
If I take 30 steps linearly -- one, two, three, four, five --
إذا أخذت 30 خطوة خطيا، واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة، خمسة
I get to 30.
أصل إلى 30
If I take 30 steps exponentially -- two, four, eight, 16 --
إذا أخذت 30 خطوة أسيا، اثنان، أربعة، ثمانية، 16
I get to a billion.
أصل إلى بليون
It makes a huge difference.
ذلك فرق هائل
And that really describes information technology.
وهذا يصف حقيقتا تقنية المعلومات
When I was a student at MIT,
حين كنت تلميذا في جامعة إم آي تي
we all shared one computer that took up a whole building.
تشاركنا جميعا في حاسب واحد بحجم مبنى كامل
The computer in your cellphone today is a million times cheaper,
الحاسب في جوالك اليوم أرخص بمليون مرة
a million times smaller,
أصغر بمليون مرة
a thousand times more powerful.
أقوى بألف مرة
That's a billion-fold increase in capability per dollar
هذا تضخم ببليون مرة في القدرة للدولار الواحد
that we've actually experienced since I was a student.
منذ أن كنت طالبا
And we're going to do it again in the next 25 years.
وسنقوم بذلك مجددا في الـ 25 عام القادمة
Information technology progresses
تتقدم تقنية المعلومات
through a series of S-curves
في سلسلة من منحنيات على شكل "S"
where each one is a different paradigm.
لكل منها نموذج مختلف
So people say, "What's going to happen when Moore's Law comes to an end?"
فيقول الناس "ماذا سيحدث حين يصل قانون موور للنهاية"ـ
Which will happen around 2020.
والذي سيحدث حول 2020
We'll then go to the next paradigm.
سننتقل حينها للنموذج التالي
And Moore's Law was not the first paradigm
مع العلم أن قانون موور لم يكن النموذج الأول
to bring exponential growth to computing.
ليطبق النمو الأسي على الحاسبات
The exponential growth of computing started
لقد بدأ نمو الحاسبات
decades before Gordon Moore was even born.
قبل عقود من مولد جوردن موور
And it doesn't just apply to computation.
وهذا لا ينطبق فقط على الحسابات
It's really any technology where we can measure
هي في الواقع أي تقنية يمكننا قياس
the underlying information properties.
خصائص المعلومات
Here we have 49 famous computers. I put them in a logarithmic graph.
لدينا هنا 49 حاسب مشهور. وضعتهم على مقياس لوغارثمي
The logarithmic scale hides the scale of the increase,
يخفي المقياس اللوغارثمي حجم الزيادة
because this represents trillions-fold increase
لأن هذا يمثل زيادة تريلون ضعف
since the 1890 census.
منذ تعداد 1890
In 1950s they were shrinking vacuum tubes,
في الخمسينات كانوا يصغرون حجم الأنابيب المفرغة
making them smaller and smaller. They finally hit a wall;
لجعلها أصغر وأصغر. ووصلوا إلى حائط
they couldn't shrink the vacuum tube any more and keep the vacuum.
لا يمكنهم تقليص الأنابيب المفرغة والمحافظة على الفراغ
And that was the end of the shrinking of vacuum tubes,
وكان ذلك نهاية تقليص الأنابيب المفرغة
but it was not the end of the exponential growth of computing.
ولكنها لم تكن نهاية النمو الأسي للحاسبات
We went to the fourth paradigm, transistors,
انتقلنا إلى النموذج الرابع، الترانزيستور
and finally integrated circuits.
ومؤخرا الدوائر المدمجة
When that comes to an end we'll go to the sixth paradigm;
حين يصل ذلك إلى النهاية سننتقل إلى النموذج السادس
three-dimensional self-organizing molecular circuits.
دوائر جزيئية ثلاثية الأبعاد ذاتية التنظيم
But what's even more amazing, really, than this
ولكن المثير حقا، أكثر من هذا
fantastic scale of progress,
التطور المذهل
is that -- look at how predictable this is.
هو مدى سهولة التنبؤ بذلك
I mean this went through thick and thin,
أعني أننا خلال السراء والضراء
through war and peace, through boom times and recessions.
خلال الحرب والسلم، خلال الازدهار والركود
The Great Depression made not a dent in this exponential progression.
الكساد الكبير لم يخدش هذا التقدم الأسي
We'll see the same thing in the economic recession we're having now.
وسنرى نفس الشيء في الكساد الاقتصادي الحالي
At least the exponential growth of information technology capability
النمو الأسي لقدرات تقنية المعلومات
will continue unabated.
ستستمر دون رادع
And I just updated these graphs.
وقد حدثت هذه البيانات
Because I had them through 2002 in my book, "The Singularity is Near."
لأنها كانت إلى 2002 في كتابي، التفرد قادم
So we updated them,
فحدثناها
so I could present it here, to 2007.
لأتمكن من عرضها هنا حتى 2007
And I was asked, "Well aren't you nervous?
وقد سئلت "ألست متوترا؟
Maybe it kind of didn't stay on this exponential progression."
فقد لا تكون قد التزمت بذلك النمو الأسي"ـ
I was a little nervous
كنت قلقا بعض الشيء
because maybe the data wouldn't be right,
لأن البيانات قد لا تكون صحيحة
but I've done this now for 30 years,
ولكنني أقوم بهذا منذ 30 عام
and it has stayed on this exponential progression.
وقد بقيت على هذا النمو الأسي
Look at this graph here.You could buy one transistor for a dollar in 1968.
انظروا إلى هذا الرسم هنا. في عام 1968 يمكنك شراء ترانزيستور بدولار
You can buy half a billion today,
يمكنك شراء نصف بليون اليوم
and they are actually better, because they are faster.
وهي في الواقع أفضل، لأنها أسرع
But look at how predictable this is.
ولكن انظروا إلى إمكانية التنبؤ
And I'd say this knowledge is over-fitting to past data.
وأقول أن هذه المعلومات مطابقة للبيانات السابقة
I've been making these forward-looking predictions for about 30 years.
أنا أقوم بهذه النظرة المستقبلية منذ 30 عام
And the cost of a transistor cycle,
وتكلفة دورة الترانزيستور
which is a measure of the price performance of electronics,
وهي مقياس التكلفة للأداء في الإلكترونيات
comes down about every year.
تنخفض كل عام
That's a 50 percent deflation rate.
بمعدل تقلص 50 في المائة
And it's also true of other examples,
وهذا أيضا صحيح لأمثلة أخرى
like DNA data or brain data.
كبيانات الحمض النووي أو الدماغ
But we more than make up for that.
ولكننا عوضنا عن ذلك وأكثر
We actually ship more than twice as much
نحن نشحن أكثر من ضعف الكمية
of every form of information technology.
من كل أشكال تقنية المعلومات
We've had 18 percent growth in constant dollars
لدينا زيادة 18 في المائة ثابتة من الدولار
in every form of information technology for the last half-century,
في كل أشكال تقنية المعلومات خلال نصف القرن الماضي
despite the fact that you can get twice as much of it each year.
بخلاف أنك تستطيع شراء ضعف الكمية كل عام
This is a completely different example.
هذا مثال مختلف تماما
This is not Moore's Law.
هذا ليس قانون موور
The amount of DNA data
كمية بيانات الحمض النووي
we've sequenced has doubled every year.
التي قمنا بترتيبها تضاعف كل عام
The cost has come down by half every year.
التكلفة انخفضت للنصف كل عام
And this has been a smooth progression
وكان هذا تقدما سلسا
since the beginning of the genome project.
منذ بداية مشروع الجينوم
And halfway through the project, skeptics said,
وفي نصف مشوار المشروع، قال المشككون
"Well, this is not working out. You're halfway through the genome project
هذا لا يجدي. لقد مضى نصف المشروع
and you've finished one percent of the project."
وقد أنهينا واحد في المائة فقط من المشروع
But that was really right on schedule.
ولكن كان ذلك في الحقيقة على الجدول
Because if you double one percent seven more times,
لأنك إذا ضاعفت واحد سبع مرات أخرى
which is exactly what happened,
وهو تماما ما حدث
you get 100 percent. And the project was finished on time.
تحصل على 100 في المائة. وإنتها المشروع في وقته
Communication technologies:
تقنية الاتصالات
50 different ways to measure this,
توجد 50 طريقة لقياس هذا
the number of bits being moved around, the size of the Internet.
عدد البيانات التي تتنقل، حجم الإنترنت
But this has progressed at an exponential pace.
ولكن هذا تقدم بسرعة أسية
This is deeply democratizing.
هذا يعمق الديمقراطية
I wrote, over 20 years ago in "The Age of Intelligent Machines,"
كتبت، منذ 20 عام في عصر الآلات الذكية
when the Soviet Union was going strong, that it would be swept away
حين كان الإتحاد السوفيتي قويا، أنه سيجرف
by this growth of decentralized communication.
بهذا التضخم في الاتصالات اللامركزية
And we will have plenty of computation as we go through the 21st century
وسيكون لدينا الكثير من الحسابات في طريقنا للقرن 21
to do things like simulate regions of the human brain.
لنقوم بأمور مثل محاكاة أجزاء من العقل البشري
But where will we get the software?
ولكن من أين سنحصل على البرمجيات
Some critics say, "Oh, well software is stuck in the mud."
قال بعض النقاد "آه، البرمجيات عالقة بالوحل"ـ
But we are learning more and more about the human brain.
ولكننا نتعلم أكثر وأكثر عن العقل البشري
Spatial resolution of brain scanning is doubling every year.
دقة مسح العقل تتضاعف كل عام
The amount of data we're getting about the brain is doubling every year.
كمية البيانات التي نحصل عليها عن الدماغ تتضاعف كل عام
And we're showing that we can actually turn this data
والآن نعمل لتحويل هذه البيانات إلى
into working models and simulations of brain regions.
نماذج ومحاكاة لأجزاء العقل المختلفة
There is about 20 regions of the brain that have been modeled,
هناك حوالي 20 جزء من العقل تمت نمذجتها
simulated and tested:
محاكاتها وتجربتها
the auditory cortex, regions of the visual cortex;
القشرة السمعية، مناطق من القشرة البصرية
cerebellum, where we do our skill formation;
المخيخ، حيث نقوم بتكوين المهارات
slices of the cerebral cortex, where we do our rational thinking.
شرائح من القشرة الدماغية، حيث نقوم بالتفكير العقلاني
And all of this has fueled
وكل هذا قد غذى
an increase, very smooth and predictable, of productivity.
وزاد، بسلاسة وتوقع، للإنتاج
We've gone from 30 dollars to 130 dollars
انتقلنا من 30 دولار إلى 130 دولار
in constant dollars in the value of an average hour of human labor,
من حيث قيمة ساعة من العمل الإنساني
fueled by this information technology.
غذي بتقنية المعلومات هذه
And we're all concerned about energy and the environment.
وجميعنا قلقين بخصوص الطاقة والبيئة
Well this is a logarithmic graph.
هذا رسم لوغريثمي
This represents a smooth doubling,
هذا يمثل مضاعفة سلسة
every two years, of the amount of solar energy we're creating,
كل عامين، لكمية الطاقة الشمسية التي ننتجها
particularly as we're now applying nanotechnology,
خصوصا الآن مع تطبيقاتنا لتكنولوجيا النانو
a form of information technology, to solar panels.
نوع من تقنية المعلومات، للألواح الشمسية
And we're only eight doublings away
ونحن على بعد ثمان مضاعفات فقط
from it meeting 100 percent of our energy needs.
من تحقيق 100 في المائة من احتياجاتنا للطاقة
And there is 10 thousand times more sunlight than we need.
وهناك 10 آلاف ضعف عن احتياجنا من ضوء الشمس
We ultimately will merge with this technology. It's already very close to us.
فنخن سوف نصل إلى هذه التقنية. وهي قريبة جدا
When I was a student it was across campus, now it's in our pockets.
حين كنت طالبا كانت في آخر المجمع. الآن تقبع في جيبي
What used to take up a building now fits in our pockets.
ما كان يأخذ مباني الآن يدخل في جيوبنا
What now fits in our pockets would fit in a blood cell in 25 years.
ما يدخل في جيوبنا اليوم سيدخل في خلية دم بعد 25 عام
And we will begin to actually deeply influence
وسنبدأ حقيقتا في التأثير بعمق
our health and our intelligence,
على صحتنا وذكائنا
as we get closer and closer to this technology.
ونحن نقترب أكثر وأكثر من هذه التقنية
Based on that we are announcing, here at TED,
بناءا على ذلك نعلن، هنا من تيد
in true TED tradition, Singularity University.
بتقاليد تيد أصيلة، جامعة التفرد
It's a new university
إنها جامعة جديدة
that's founded by Peter Diamandis, who is here in the audience,
أسسها بيتر دايمانديز، وهو هنا بين الحضور
and myself.
وأنا
It's backed by NASA and Google,
مدعوم من ناسا وجوجل
and other leaders in the high-tech and science community.
وقادة آخرون من التقنية والعلوم
And our goal was to assemble the leaders,
وهدفنا كان جمع القادة
both teachers and students,
من الطلاب والمعلمين
in these exponentially growing information technologies,
في هذه التقنيات المعلوماتية المتضاعفة
and their application.
وتطبيقاتها
But Larry Page made an impassioned speech
ولكن لاري بيج ألقى كلمة مؤثرة
at our organizing meeting,
في اجتماعنا التأسيسي
saying we should devote this study
قائلا أننا يجب أن نوجه هذه الدراسة
to actually addressing some of the major challenges facing humanity.
لمواجهة بعض الصعاب الرئيسية التي تواجه البشرية
And if we did that, then Google would back this.
وإذا قمنا بذلك، ستقوم جوجل بدعمنا
And so that's what we've done.
فكان هذا ما فعلنا
The last third of the nine-week intensive summer session
الثلث الأخير من برنامج التسع أسابيع المكثف
will be devoted to a group project to address
سيكون مخصصا لمشروع جماعي لمواجهة
some major challenge of humanity.
بعض التحديات البشرية العظمى
Like for example, applying the Internet,
مثل، تطبيق الإنترنت
which is now ubiquitous, in the rural areas of China or in Africa,
وهو الآن في كل مكان، في المناطق القروية من الصين وأفريقيا
to bringing health information
لإيصال معلومات صحية
to developing areas of the world.
للمناطق النامية من العالم
And these projects will continue past these sessions,
وهذه المشاريع ستستمر بعد هذه الجلسات
using collaborative interactive communication.
باستخدام الاتصال التفاعلي التعاوني
All the intellectual property that is created and taught
جميع الحقوق الفكرية التي تنتج وتدرس
will be online and available,
ستكون متاحة على النت
and developed online in a collaborative fashion.
وتنتج على النت بطريقة تعاونية
Here is our founding meeting.
هذا هو اجتماعنا التأسيسي
But this is being announced today.
ولكن هذا سيعلن اليوم
It will be permanently headquartered in Silicon Valley,
سيكون مقره الرئيسي في سيلكون فالي
at the NASA Ames research center.
في مركز أبحاث ناسا
There are different programs for graduate students,
هناك برامج مختلفة لطلاب الدراسات العليا
for executives at different companies.
للتنفيذيين في الشركات المختلفة
The first six tracks here -- artificial intelligence,
البرامج الست الأولى هنا، الذكاء الصناعي
advanced computing technologies, biotechnology, nanotechnology --
تقنيات الحسابات المتقدمة، التقنية الحيوية، تقنية النانو
are the different core areas of information technology.
هي المجالات الرئيسية المختلفة في تقنية المعلومات
Then we are going to apply them to the other areas,
ثم سنقوم بتطبيقها في مجالات أخرى
like energy, ecology,
مثل الطاقة، البيئة
policy law and ethics, entrepreneurship,
القانون والأخلاقيات، وروح المبادرة
so that people can bring these new technologies to the world.
ليتمكن الناس من تقديم هذه التقنيات الحديثة للعالم
So we're very appreciative of the support we've gotten
لذا فنحن نقدر الدعم الذي حصلنا عليه
from both the intellectual leaders, the high-tech leaders,
من قادة الفكر، قادة التقنيات المتقدمة
particularly Google and NASA.
تحديدا من جوجل وناسا
This is an exciting new venture.
هذا مشروع جديد مثير
And we invite you to participate. Thank you very much.
وندعوكم للمشاركة. شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)